It is well known that our bloodline dates back
.to the long-past Heian period.
遥か平安時代から
我々の血脈が続いているのは明白である
Just because we're tanuki
いかに我々が狸といえども
doesn't mean we pop out of a nook in a
.camphor tree like a hairy ball of candy.
楠の洞から毛深い飴のように
むくむくと浮世に押し出されてきたわけではない
The wildly branching bloodline we inherit
受け継がれて野放図に枝分かれした血脈は
also binds us in some way.
そこはかとなく我々を縛る
Even a bohemian tanuki like me
私のようなボヘミアン狸ですら
cannot abandon his blood ties so easily.
軽々に捨てられないのが血縁というものであり
As you might expect,
なまじ血脈があるだけに
ささやかな諍いが便所に流せず
even the most tenuous familial bonds
.can allow grudges to be held,
turning quarrels that should be water
.under the bridge into long-lasting feuds.
水ならぬ 血で血を洗う争いとなることもある
They say that blood is thicker than water,
血は水よりも濃い とは
あはははは ははは
but I think that proverb
.is more than I can handle.
私の手に余る言葉だ
ははは
面白くない世の中
omoshiroku nai yo no naka
You just have to make
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
面白くすればいいさ
omoshiroku sureba ii sa
this dull world more interesting
tsumaranee no ga kuchiguse nano wa
Some people love to claim that something is boring
“つまらねえ”のが口癖なのは
tsumaranee no ga kuchiguse nano wa
Some people love to claim that something is boring
それこそホントにつまらない
sore koso honto ni tsumaranai
That habit is the most boring thing of all
文句を言うのは簡単だけど
monku wo iu no wa kantan dakedo
It's easy to complain about stuff
誰かは何もくれない
dareka wa nannmo kurenai
but it doesn't do any good at all
走らないけど止まりはしない
hashiranai kedo tomari wa shinai
That sort of useless waste of time
dare ni mo nagareru ahou no chi
runs in our idiot blood
誰にも流れる阿呆の血
sawageba sawagu hodo kakitateru
Just party on and on, and the more you do
騒げば騒ぐ程かき立てる
なんと素晴らしき日々
nanto subarashiki hibi
the more awesome will be your days
omoshiroku nai yo no naka
You just have to make
面白くない世の中
omoshiroku sureba ii no sa
this dull world more interesting
面白くすればいいのさ
jibun de mitsukerya
The things you find for yourself in this world
自分で見つけりゃ
ほどほどにパラダイスだ
hodohodo ni paradaisu da
quickly turn it into a little paradise
ki ga tsukeba itsu datte
Before you know it,
気がつけば何時だって
ki ga tsukeba itsu datte
Before you know it,
uchouten jinsei da
you live a life of pure ecstasy
有頂天人生だ
uchouten jinsei da
you live a life of pure ecstasy
Episode Seven
Bathhouse Rules
Akegarasu
Did you find what you were looking for?
探し物は見つかったかい？
I don't have the slightest of leads.
まだ手がかりすらない
I gotta say, I thought you'd
.already ended up in a stew.
しっかしお前はもう
鍋にされて喰われたと思っていたよ
ま いずれそうなるだろうから大した違いは無いがね
Well, I'm sure it's only a matter of time.
ひどいことを仰る
With all due respect, what the hell?
Drink up while you still can.
酒は飲めるうちに飲んでおくことだ
You gotta seize the day, you know.
生きている喜びを噛みしめろ
ん ん？
Big bro, you gotta help me!
兄ちゃん 助けておくれよ
He hates baths. To an extreme degree.
風呂嫌い ここに極まれり
These days, even the tanuki
who live out in Shimogamo Forest
下鴨の森をねぐらにする狸でさえも
worry about split ends
.and use hair conditioner,
枝毛を気にしてトリートメントを使う
ご時世であるというのに
but this guy can't even stand to
.wipe his body with a damp cloth.
濡れ手ぬぐいで体を拭くのも嫌がる程だ
だからなんだ
Oh, that explains a lot.
銭湯へ行きましょうって言っても
天気が悪い 尻が痒い
Whenever I say "Let's go
.to the bathhouse," he's like,
"The weather's bad."
"My butt itches."
"My back hurts."
腰が痛い お前の顔つきが気に入らん
"I don't like the look on your face!"
って
Didn't you try dragging him out anyway?
無理に引っ張り出そうとしなかったか
I did! Then he threw a
.huge daruma doll at me.
したよ？　したら重い達磨を投げられた
それでも何かが発酵したような
奥深い香りが立ち込めてきたから
Anyway, the whole room smells
.like something died in there,
so I tried to do something about it, but...
なんとかしようとしたんだけど
But he's been spraying so much air freshener
around that you can't even breathe?
香水を振りまくばかりで息すらできなくなったか
Yeah.
うん
I'm so useless, big bro.
兄ちゃん 僕は役立たずだ
I can't even get Master
.Akadama to take a bath.
先生をお風呂に入れる才能も無いんだ
Don't cry, Yashirou.
-泣くな矢四郎 そんな才能は無用の長物だ
-う う
Herding seniors isn't the
.most sought-after of talents.
You've got better things
.to put your energy into.
お前には他に身につけるべきことがある
He's been letting loose
.with his tengu winds, too.
先生は天狗風を吹かすんだよ？
Oh, he still has enough energy to do that?
おや 先生にもまだそんな余力が？
It's messing up my hair.
僕の毛をチリチリにするんだ
Any more, and I'll end up with an afro.
このままだと僕はアフロになる
こんなちびっ子相手に
残り少ない本領を発揮するとは
If he wants to show off what's left of his power,
he should pick on someone his own size.
He's a disgrace to all tengu.
天狗の風上にも置けん先生だ
熱々のお湯に叩き込んでやる
I'll plunge him into the
steaming bathwater of repentance!
You shouldn't bully him too much, big bro.
でも兄ちゃん あんまり先生をいじめてはいけないよ
I know.
分かってる 言ってみただけだ
I just wanted to say that.
はう
んん
ん
Hey, your tail's out.
おい 尻尾
ん？
は
うっ
ああ
That you, Yasaburou?
矢三郎か
I haven't seen you since the
.night of the Fire Festival.
送り火の宵からとんと姿を見かけなかったが
どこで遊び呆けておった？
Where have you been loafing about?
You're a rambunctious lowlife who's
.forgotten how to act toward his mentor.
師への礼儀も弁えん奴め 遊ぶことしか念頭にない
I wasn't exactly loafing around, but...
遊んでおったわけではないのですが
ともかくご無沙汰いたしました
Anyway, I apologize for not visiting sooner.
I have no need of your visits.
沙汰は無用だ
すう はあ
In fact, it was one less thing to worry about.
せいせいしておったのだからな
Oh, you're always saying stuff like that.
またそのようなことを
Why don't you just admit you were lonely?
寂しかったと仰ればよいのに
As if!
-たわけ
-うう
Why does someone like me have to
go take a bath with you tanuki?
何故わしともあろうものが
狸ごときに付き添われて風呂に行かねばならんのだ
You don't want to go with us?
我々と出掛けるのが嫌なのですか
Is that it?
そうなのですか　では弁天様となら行くのですか
So you'd go if it were with Benten?
That goes without saying.
言うまでもない 望むところだ
That's exactly what I want.
You lecherous tengu.
この助平天狗め
In that case, how about
I transform into Benten?
ならば私が弁天様に化けてみせましょう
It'll be nice and sexy.
ぷりっとエロティックに
Just you try it.
そんなことをしてみろ 捻り潰してくれる
I'll pulverize you!
Do it if you can, you stubborn old tengu!
やれるもんならやってみろ この偏屈ジジイ
You asked for it.
-く 言いおったな
-ん
The likes of you don't stand a
chance against my tengu wind!
その気になればお前らなんぞ
天狗風で一捻りであるぞ
Bring it!
どんと来い
Moo!
ぶもー
んん むう
Moo.
ぶもー
かーっ
Mooo...
ぶー
...o.
も
んん
Moo.
ぶも
ふふ
ずびび
Moo.
ぶも
Moo!
ぶもー
矢三郎 そんな所で何を遊んでおるか
Yasaburou, what are you
playing at over there?
Please, no moo-re.
もー
Enough with the mooing already.
もーもー言うでない
Master, might you be
sweating with righteous fury?
先生 お怒りになって汗などおかきではないですか
Eh.
うむ
It's not so bad to have a bath
every now and then, you know?
たまにはひとっ風呂浴びるのも良いものですよ
うむ
Eh.
ん
Master, it's been quite some time.
先生 お久しぶりでございます
It's pretty chilly tonight, isn't it, Yaichirou?
寒いな 矢一郎よ
Yes, Master.
はい 先生
Must be a pain coming
all the way out here, huh?
面倒なこっちゃと思うておるな
Not at all.
滅相もございません
Say what you really think.
正直に言え
I'm speaking from the heart.
本心から言っています
Well, whatever.
まあ良いわ
んん
Okay, let's go!
いざゆかん　何をぐずぐずしておる
What are we dawdling around for?
Bathhouse
What a bother. Such a bother.
億劫なりな 億劫なりと
Bathhouse
men
Wo
んん
ぐ はあ
ん うう んあ
ああ
あ？
んん
んむ
ん あっ
兄ちゃんこのお風呂冷めてるよ？
This bath's cold, big bro!
Yashirou, that one's supposed to be cold.
矢四郎 それは始めから水なのだよ
何故お前らのような毛玉風情と
風呂に入らねばならんのだ
Why do I have to take a
bath with you hairballs?
We're in human form,
so shedding is not a concern.
人間に化けておりますゆえ
毛が散る懸念は無用にございます
どうせなら弁天に背中を流してもらいたいものだ
Still, I wish Benten were here
.to wash my back.
I want to take a bath with Benten.
わしは弁天と風呂に入りたい
Ahh, I wanna take a bath with Benten!
ああ 弁天と風呂に入りたいのう
Master, must you express your
indecent desires so openly?
先生 そんなわいせつな欲望をむき出しに
Please try to retain at least a little dignity.
少しは体面を守る努力をなさってください
I'm ashamed to call myself your disciple.
弟子として情けない
大体弁天様と一緒に来たって
先生が女湯に入るわけにはいかんですよ
Even if Benten came, you think you'd be
allowed to join her in the women's bath?
が
Quiet, you.
やかましい
矢三郎よ
Yasaburou,
I hear you were out the other day
.with Benten and the Friday Fellows.
お前先日弁天と
金曜倶楽部へ出掛けたというではないか
You certainly seem to be obsessed
.with following her around.
どうもお前はむやみに弁天に付きまとう癖がある
There's no way a hairball like you would
be carrying a torch for her... is there?
毛玉風情がまさかあれに
恋情を抱いておるわけではあるまいな
Don't be ridiculous!
とんでもない　狸が人間に惚れてどうするのです
What'd be the point of a
tanuki falling for a human?
掟破りの恋ですか
The allure of forbidden love?
Like you give a damn
.about what tanuki forbid.
狸の掟など屁とも思っておらんだろう
お前のようなひねくれ者は
何を企てるか分かったものではない
Who knows what a twisted guy
.like you might be plotting.
また妙なところだけ買いかぶる
Your expectations of me
.are always so warped.
I'm only trying to look out for you.
お前の身の上を心配して言うのではないか
If you view her as just some human girl,
you'll get eaten up.
たかが人間の小娘と侮っていると喰われてしまうぞ
Master!
先生
It's about time to get out.
もうそろそろ出ましょう
ああ お前が風呂に入れと言うからわざわざ来たのに
First you drag me all the way here,
and now you won't even let me
take my time in the bath?
ゆっくり体も洗わせないのか
He says he hates baths,
風呂嫌いのくせに
一旦入ると長風呂になるんだから もう
but once he gets in,
you can't get him out.
ごく ごく
It's sweet.
甘いね
Sure is.
甘いのう
兄ちゃん コーヒーも牛乳も美味しくないのに
コーヒー牛乳はどうして美味しいの？
Big bro, coffee and milk both taste bad,
so why does coffee milk taste so good?
It must be the multiplier effect.
ん それは相乗効果さ
相乗効果？
The multiplier effect?
Like a fateful encounter.
運命の出会いということだ
Once they meet, everything goes smoothly.
そうなると何でもうまくいくものだ
先生はあんなこと仰るけど
本当は兄ちゃんが好きなんだ
You know, Master says a lot of things,
but he really does like you.
ごく ごく　はあ は
俺だってそれは先刻承知さ
Yeah. I knew that already.
兄ちゃんだって先生が好きだね
And you like Master too, right?
Hey, keep that between us, okay?
おい そんなこと誰にも言うなよ？
My dignity is at stake here.
沽券に関わるからな
While you were in Osaka,
he kept asking me,
兄ちゃんが大阪へ行ってた間
先生は僕にいっつも仰ってたよ
"How is Yasaburou doing?
Did Benten eat him yet?"
矢三郎はどうしてる 弁天に喰われておらんかって
That's good to hear.
ありがたいこっちゃ
ん？
おお わっしょい
う う
わあ　あ う
く
What's all this?
何事だ
Are the tanuki acting like idiots again?
狸どもがまたバカをやっておるな？
ん
The Ebisugawa Elite Guard?
夷川親衛隊か!?
Togetsukyou
Bridge
The Ebisugawa Elite Guard?
夷川親衛隊か
親衛隊？
Elite Guard?
Just some hoodlums that were
.lured in with free fake Denki Bran.
ただで飲める偽電気ブランに惹かれて
集まっただけの愚連隊だ
As if getting Master Akadama to
.take a bath wasn't enough of a hassle,
先生を風呂に入れるだけでも億劫なのに
阿呆兄弟まで現れるとは
now these numbskull
.brothers show up as well.
これこそ負の相乗効果と言うべきか
This is what you'd call
.the anti-multiplier effect.
Did you do something?
何かやったのか？
はあ 叔父上の命令で手を引けと言いに来たんだろう
Uncle probably ordered them to come here
.and convince me to drop out of the race.
The next Nise-emon
.will be selected this month,
今月次の偽右衛門が選ばれる
俺と叔父上のどちらに決まるか
予断を許さん状況だからな
and there's no telling
.whether it'll be Uncle or me.
I'm runnin' around all by myself
俺一人で走り回ってるんだぞ
誰も手伝ってくれないからだ
'cause nobody ever helps me out!
Seriously, you brothers of mine are such—
全く 俺の弟たちはどいつもこいつも
This again?
またそれかよ
You just up and left for Osaka without
a single thought for your own brother!
お前も俺の苦境を尻目に大阪なんぞに逃げやがって
命が危なかったんだからやむを得ん
What could I do? My life was in danger.
元はと言えばお前がな
But you're the one who got into this—
待て兄貴 見ろよ
Wait, bro. Look.
ん
It's Kinkaku!
金閣だよ
And Ginkaku!
銀閣だよ
言われなくとも分かる
Yeah, we know.
You don't have to announce it.
Then I'm sure you also
.know what we came to say.
それならば
僕らが言いに来たことも分かってるはずだね
And you think I'm just gonna
do you a favor and drop out?
俺が素直に手を引くと思ってるのか
ふふん
We thought you might say that.
多分そう言うだろうと思っていたけれどもね
But according to my carefully
.composed calculations,
でも 僕が冷静沈着に計算したところによると
your chances of winning
.are infinitesimal.
あんたが勝つ見込みは無いんだな
You may not know this, but Yoshidayama
.has promised to back the Ebisugawa family.
知らないだろうけど 吉田山は夷川家についたし
それにね えーっと 宝ヶ池も僕らの味方になる
Moreover... Let's see.
Takaragaike is backing us too.
We even have a significant
.amount of support from Yase.
八瀬からだって応援がぞろぞろ来るよ？
Gosho will back me,
御所は俺についた
南禅寺だってお前らの味方にはならん
and Nanzenji would never take your side.
If Nanzenji's with me,
then Ginkakuji will be too.
南禅寺がそうなら銀閣寺だってそうだ
必然的に高台寺も六波羅も俺につく
Koudaiji and Rokuhara will
.undoubtedly support me as well.
そうかもしれないけど？
That may be the case...
Wait, really? That many?
そうかもしれないけど　それ本当？　そんなに？
That's not what I'd heard.
話が違うな　驚天動地だ
This is earth-shattering.
Big bro, don't give up now! Go for the kill!
兄さん負けるな やってしまえ
僕らには奥の手があるんだ
We have an ace in the hole, remember?
That's right. Our ace in the hole!
そうなんだ 奥の手奥の手
And what would that be?
何だそれは
I just said it was our ace in the hole.
これはもう奥の手だから
そう簡単に見せるわけにはいかないさ
You don't expect me to come out
and tell you, do you?
Because I certainly won't.
だから教えてやらない
But I will tell you that
.you should drop out now.
教えてやらないけど降参しろ？
The only one who can unite
.all tanuki-kind is our dad,
狸界を束ねられるのは僕らの父上だけだし
and one day I'll follow in his footsteps.
ゆくゆくは僕がその跡を継ぐんだ
The world has no further use for the pathetic
.young masters of the Shimogamo family.
下鴨家の情けないお坊ちゃまたちには
もう用は無いのさ
そうとも
Quite right!
か うう くうう
えや
が がおお
ええ
どすこい
Fragile
False Advertising
You might have a mind to bite our butts again,
but it's not gonna happen.
Fragile
False Advertising
またお尻を噛もうったって そうはいかない
Fragile
False Advertising
An artisan blacksmith residing in Nagahama
.reluctantly made us this iron underwear.
Fragile
False Advertising
これこそが長浜在住の鍛冶職人が渋々作った
鉄のパンツだ
Fragile
False Advertising
If you try to bite us again,
you'll only chip those fangs of yours.
お前ががぶりとやったところで
歯が欠けるのがオチだぞ
Fragile
False Advertising
How's that for an idea?
どうだいこのアイディアは 兄さんは賢いだろう？
My big bro sure is clever, isn't he?
And trying to use force
.will get you nowhere.
無理に脱がそうとしても無駄さ
自分でも簡単には脱げないんだから
We have trouble taking
.them off ourselves.
Thanks to you, my big bro and I have caught a chill
.and are in considerable distress.
おかげで腹が冷え冷えで
兄さんも僕も大変な苦しみを味わっている
Quite right!
そうとも
In fact, I'm now more aware of
.that crisis than ever, big bro.
今そこにある危機に思い至ってしまったよ 兄さん
I guess you could say I'm about to be
.yelling "Oh crap!" quite literally.
ちょっと危機一髪な感じがしてきた 軽くやばい
Now that you mention it, me too.
あっ 実を言うと僕もだ
あっ す はあ あ 早く さあ 偽右衛門にならないと言え
So, come on. Just tell us you'll
.drop out of the Nise-emon race.
すう　早く言わないと あっあ 大変なことになるぞ
Otherwise, things are about
.to get real messy in here.
Like we care.
いいよ別に
-うう　う う
-あっ え？　あ ちょ あ ああ あ
がお
ああ
Damn you guys!
こいつらめ　はぐ
あ あ
あああ
Cease that infernal racket!
うるさいわい
-んん
-どす
どすこい どすこい どすこい どすこい どすこい
どすこい どすこい どすこい どす
ふん
金閣よ 銭湯の掟を知らんのか？
Kinkaku, don't you know the bathhouse rules?
第一に 湯船でタオルを使ってはならん
Rule one: no towels in the bathtub.
Rule two: no washing clothes in the water.
第二に洗濯をしてはならん
And finally, rule three: you have to
.rinse off before getting in the bath.
そして 第三に湯に入る前には
必ずかかり湯をしなくてはならん
You can't just hop in like that.
いきなり飛び込んではいかんのだ
You think a fool who can't even
follow the bathhouse rules
湯の使い方も知らん愚か者が
-洛中の狸の長になれると思ってるのか
-うううううう
could ever become the leader
of all Kyoto's tanuki?
ごほ ごほ ごほ
だってあんたが放り込んだんじゃないか
But you're the one who threw me in.
It's not like I did it myself.
僕は自分で入りやしないよ
Well, whatever.
まあそれはいい それで 奥の手とは何だ？
What's this "ace in the hole" of yours?
言わないもんね
I said I wasn't telling.
そうか
I see.
Lips still sealed, huh?
言わぬか
あああああ あ あ う うはい
If you don't tell me, I'll throw you in
.and seal the lid on this.
-言わないとここへ放り込んで蓋をするぞ？
-う うはい うはい　うはい はははい うははい
Then you'll really catch a chill.
-それはもう腹が冷えるぞ？
-はあ はい　はい
Okay, fine! I'll talk.
分かったよ 言うよ 僕はお腹が痛いよ
My stomach hurts, sheesh!
It's about your old man.
あんたたちの親父のことだ 何で死んだか知ってる？
Do you know how he died?
Why bring that up now?
何を今更　父上は鍋にされたのだ
He was cooked in a stew.
く おかしいとは思わないのかい？
Don't you find that suspicious?
How were they able to catch
such a great tanuki so easily?
あれほどの大狸が何であっさりと人間に捕まるんだい
Bath
Cold
I happen to be quite sharp,
so I found this rather curious.
僕は頭脳明晰だからこれはおかしいと思ったんだ
So I decided to do some
.investigating with Ginkaku.
それで銀閣と一緒に調べてみたのさ
And we figured it out.
そしたら分かった
What did you figure out?
何が分かったというんだ
A truth that, should it be exposed,
この事実が暴露されたら下鴨家は
二度と立ち直れないこと請け合いだな
would deal a fatal blow
.to the Shimogamo family.
Are you sure you want to know?
それでもいいのか
何だと言うんだ
What are you saying?!
伯父さん
As it turns out, the day Uncle Shimogamo Souichirou
.was caught by the Friday Fellows,
下鴨総一郎は金曜倶楽部に捕まった日
夜更けまで誰かと一緒にお酒を飲んでいたらしい
he was out late drinking with someone.
He got so drunk that he became careless.
だから ぐでんぐでんに酔っ払って油断しちゃったんだね
And that cost him his life.
お酒が命取りだったんだ
So?
それが？
Well, you see,
それなのにだね
その夜に一緒にお酒を飲んでいた相手は
今までずーっとだんまりだ
the one he went drinking with that night has
.remained utterly quiet about it ever since.
Isn't that unforgivable?
僕は許せないね
Anyone decent would feel some responsibility
and apologize to everyone, right?
本来なら 責任を感じて皆に謝るべきだろ？
To their fellow tanuki!
同じ狸としてさ
After all, Uncle was a leader
to us all, was he not?
伯父さんは皆の頭領だったんだから
Who was it, then?
ん その相手は誰だ　はっきり言え！
Spit it out!
Cold
Bath
ん？　あはは
Your useless little brother—
あんたの役立たずな弟さ
Our well-dwelling friend, Yajirou!
井戸の底にいる矢二郎だよ
-な！
-へへへ
-あ
-えへへ えへ えへへへ
へへへ　えへへへ　あ？
-あ？ ああ ああっ
-く くう
ああ
Cold! It's cooold!
うわあ ちべたい ちべたい
くっ
はあ はあ
あ
Big bro, what's going on?
Bathhouse
兄ちゃんどうしたの？
Go home to the forest, Yashirou.
矢四郎は森へ帰れ 母上の所にいろ
Stay with Mother.
ええ？
Why'd you leave him behind?
何で矢四郎を置いてきたんだ？
I didn't have the heart to bring him.
可哀想だからだ
You're so easy on Yashirou.
兄貴は矢四郎に甘いな
No.
違う
This is for Yajirou's sake.
矢二郎のためだ
は
The
Six
Paths
Yasaburou, huh?
矢三郎かよ
Oh, and a rare appearance by Yaichirou.
矢一郎兄さんも一緒か 珍しいのう
How have you been, big bro?
兄さん 最近調子はどう？
Not much happens in a
.small world like this, I'm afraid.
世間が狭いものだからね
そうそう珍しい事件は起きないな
It's the bottom of a well, after all.
何しろ井戸の底だからね はは
そういえば 嵐山の紅葉を
一晩で落としてしまったそうじゃないか
By the way, I heard all the leaves
.in Arashiyama fell in one night.
世間が狭いくせに 情報が早い
You're quite well informed for
.someone living in such a small world.
Kaisei told me about it when
.she was here yesterday.
昨日海星が来て喋っていったよ
Hey, big bro...
ねえ 兄さん
何だい？
What's up?
Yajirou.
矢二郎よ
Oh, big bro.
おや 兄さん
You sound like you're in a bad mood.
えらくご機嫌の悪い声だ　何か説教をする気かい？
Have you come to
lecture me about something?
ご期待に応えられる自信が無い
I can't guarantee I'll be able to
.take your lesson to heart, though.
After all, I'm just a frog.
俺は何しろ蛙だからな
Yajirou.
矢二郎
I remember the last time
.I saw Father very clearly.
俺は父上と最後に会った日のことをよく覚えている
That day, I went out with him
.to visit the elders.
あの日 俺は父上と一緒に
長老たちの所へ出掛けていた
Afterward, he said he had
.some important appointment,
その後 父上は大切な約束があると言った
だからお前は先に帰れと言われた
so he told me to
.go home without him.
That was nothing unusual, though.
珍しいことじゃない
I mean, Father was always so busy.
父上はいつも忙しかったからな
So he accompanied me as far as Higashioji
父上は東大路まで送ってきて
俺がバスに乗り込むのを見送ってくれた
and waited until I caught the bus.
I still remember the way he looked, even now.
その姿を俺は今でも思い出す
Because that was the last time I ever saw him.
何故ならそれが
俺が見た父上の最後の姿だったからだ
Big bro...
兄さん
What I want to ask you is:
俺が聞きたいのはな
exactly where and when
did you last see Father?
お前が最後に父上に会ったのは
いつどこだったのかということだ
Were you...
お前は
Were you drinking with him that night?
あの夜 父上と一緒に酒を飲んだのか？
お前は酔っ払ったのか？
Did you get drunk?
What about him?
父上はどうした？
Did you leave Father by himself,
even though he was drunk?
お前は酔っ払った父上をそのままにしたのか？
Please tell me that's not what happened.
どうか違うと言ってくれ
Big bro, that's exactly what happened.
兄さん その通りだよ
I'm the one who sent Father to his death.
父上を死なせたのはこの俺だ
うああ
How could you?!
ああ 何ということだ う
く
この大バカ者め
You idiot!
く くう
あああ
What was I doing that day?
-私はあの日
-ああ
-何をしていたろう
-ううう う
ううう う
I was but a newborn pup, taking my
.first steps around Tadasu no Mori,
生まれたばかりの私が
ぽてぽてと糺の森を歩き出した時
when I saw Dad wave good-bye to me.
父は短いさよならをしていた
Our dad, Shimogamo Souichirou,
我が父 下鴨総一郎は
狸界を束ねる大狸だったので
was a great tanuki who united our society
and thus was extremely busy.
大変多忙であった
He was always going out,
父はしきりに出掛け
bidding farewell to the forest
.where his wife and children waited.
母と子の待つ森にサヨナラした
That's just the way it was.
そういう具合であったから
That winter,
あの冬に父が忘年会の狸鍋になって
when we found out that he had been
.cooked in a year-end stew,
この世にサヨナラしたのだと知った時
we had great difficulty understanding that
.his last parting had been a true farewell.
我々は それが本当のサヨナラであることを
飲み込むのに
骨を折った
As long as you still draw breath,
生きていく限り
there is no way to escape
.having to bid others farewell.
サヨナラという出来事と袂を分かつことはできない
It doesn't matter if you're
.human, tengu, or tanuki.
それは 人間であろうと
天狗であろうと
狸であろうと
We all have to say good-bye.
同じだ
繋いだ手を振りほどけば
You shake off my hand
tsunaida te wo furihodokeba
いたずらに 君微笑む
and idly smile at me
itazura ni kimi hohoemu
春は嵐 ざわざわする
Spring is ripe with the roll of thunder,
haru wa arashi zawazawa suru
もう花びら散りすぼんだ
and some cherry blossoms have already left the branches
mou hanabira chirisubonda
口癖はケセラセラ
Your favorite phrase is "Que será, será"
kuchiguse wa que sera sera
また呟く声がする
I can hear you whisper it again
mata tsubuyaku koe ga suru
彼女はいつもさよなら言わずに
She always vanishes
kanojo wa itsumo
sayonara
without saying "Goodbye,"
iwazu ni
風と消える
just like the wind
kaze to kieru
I don't know what the future will be like,
mirai no koto wa wakaranai keredo
未来のことはわからないけれど
今ここにある奇蹟は
but I'll have faith
ima koko ni aru
that little miracles
kiseki wa
僕のものと信じてる
are awaiting me
boku no mono to shinjiteru
約束なんてしたくないけれど
I don't want to be tied down by promises,
yakusoku nante shitakunai keredo
but let's hold up our hands
sono te wo kazashite
その手をかざして確かなもの
and find something,
tashika na mono
手に入れよう
something permanent
te ni ireyou
それは僕らを輝かす
that will
sore wa
show just who we are
bokura wo kagayakasu
蛙でなければ俺は何に化けていたろう
If not a frog, I wonder what else
.I might have transformed into.
A newt? A salamander?
イモリ？　サンショウウオ？
いずれにしても井戸に籠もったろうなぁ
I'd probably be at the bottom of a well either way.
Next Time:
The Day of Dad's Departure